av41754103 国际空间站建造过程3D动画介绍
2018年 我制作了一期视频介绍国际空间站
In 2018, I made an animation about the International Space Station.
带大家了解各个部件的组装顺序
I showed all the pieces coming together,
但其中并没有介绍具体的建造方法
but I didn't show how it was done.
这些舱段并不是自己飞过去完成对接组装的
These modules didn't just float together on their own.
实际的工作量相当大
It was a lot of work.
任务涉及到地面的任务控制中心
It involved mission controllers back on Earth,
空间站上的宇航员 和一些精巧的机器人
astronauts onboard the station, and some fancy robotics.
本期视频我们将深入了解这些任务是如何完成的
In this video, we're gonna dive deep into the details to see how it worked.
国际空间站的建造工作花费超过十年
The International Space Station took over a decade to complete.
画面中的多数部件都是由这样的航天飞机发射上去的
Most of the pieces that you see here were launched by this space shuttle.
实际上 这也正是航天飞机的主要功能
In fact, this was one of the main purposes of the space shuttle.
——建设空间站
It was to build the space station.
我们无法把每个任务都过一遍
We can't go over every single mission.
这样视频就太长了
That would take too long for this video.
我想介绍国际空间站建设的初始阶段
What I'd like to do is talk about the initial stages of the station's construction
那时还是国际空间站的幼年时期
back when the ISS was really small.
我们将回顾几个航天飞机任务 了解这些舱段与组件的组装方法
We'll go over just a few of the space shuttle missions and how these pieces were put together.
空间站不是在茫茫太空中悬停在那里的
We've got to remember, the station isn't just aimlessly floating in space.
而是以极高速度在运动
It's going incredibly fast,
大约是地面音速的20多倍
about 20 times the speed of sound here on Earth.
每90分钟绕地球一圈
It orbits the earth once every 90 minutes.
视频所示是空间站的"前向" 即它的运行方向
Here's the front of the station. It always travels in this direction.
前向 后向 左舷 右舷
So this is forward, and aft, port and starboard,
径向向外 指向远离地球的方向
and then there's zenith pointing away from the earth,
径向向内 指向地球
and nadir pointing towards the earth.
这些都是宇航员常用的词汇
These terms are part of the regular vocabulary of an astronaut.
本期视频之后也会稍稍提到
We'll be using them a little bit throughout this video.
完工后的国际空间站长这样
This is what the completed station looks like.
宇航员只能在加压舱段内生活
The only part that the astronauts can live in are the pressurized modules.
"舱段" 指画面中空间站的圆柱体部分
When I say module, I'm referring to one of these cylindrical pieces of the space station.
其中有空气可供呼吸 有舒适的生存环境
It has air to breathe, comfortable living conditions,
可以让宇航员免于暴露在真空中
and protects the astronauts from the vacuum of space.
每个舱段都有一个或多个停泊口
Each module has one or more berthing ports
可以与其他舱段连接
that can be connected to other parts of the station.
有时称为"对接口"
Sometimes these are referred to as docking ports,
但具体来讲 它应该叫停泊口
but if we're being specific, it is a berthing port
因为舱段或飞船需要机械臂的辅助才能对接
because the joining module or spacecraft must be assisted by use of a robotic arm.
空间站舱段主要分为两大部分
There are two main sections to the station,
来自俄罗斯的俄罗斯舱段
the Russian orbital segment, these are modules from Russia,
和来自美国 欧洲 日本的美国舱段
and the United States orbital segment,
these are modules from the United States, Europe, and Japan.
可以注意到两边舱段外观上的些许不同
You can see how the modules on each side look just a little bit different.
在美国段 舱段之间使用通用停泊机构(CBM)连接
On the US side, the modules are connected by the common berthing mechanism, or CBM for short.
CBM分两种 主动侧和被动侧
There are two different sides to this, the active side and the passive side.
两侧对接后 插销会将双方拉近
Once these are brought together, latches pull them in close,
之后会有16个螺栓将两者紧紧固定起来
and then there are 16 bolts to firmly mate them together.
两者中间的空间称为"前室"
The space in between is called the vestibule.
这里会用空气加压
This will be pressurized with air.
需要花费几个小时
This process takes a few hours.
然后舱门开启 移除一些设施
Then the hatch is opened, some of the hardware is removed,
再接好氧气 电力 数据与水等
and connections are made in between the modules, which includes oxygen, power, data, and water.
完成后 再用白色保护罩围上
Once finalized, there is a white protective barrier put in place.
宇航员就能自由穿行两个舱段了
The astronauts can now move freely in between the modules.
通用停泊机构用于两个永久连接的舱段之间
The common berthing mechanism is used for modules that are permanently attached together,
比如协和号节点舱与命运号实验舱
like the Harmony and Destiny modules.
还可用来服务来访的航天器 比如SpaceX的货运龙飞船
They can also be used for visiting spacecraft such as the SpaceX Cargo Dragon.
俄罗斯舱段使用的对接机构与CBM并不适配
The Russian side of the station uses a different docking mechanism that is not compatible with CBM.
所以我们需要想办法连接两种不同的机构
We need some way to connect to the different mechanisms.
类似于把美标的电器插头带到欧洲
This is kind of like taking a power plug from the United States
and bringing it over to Europe.
美标的插头插不进欧标的墙插
It's not compatible with the wall plug.
需要什么呢? 适配器
What do we need? An adapter.
国际空间站上也一样 只是尺寸更大一点
It's the same concept on the space station, but on a larger scale.
两种不同机构 中间需要适配器来连接
Two different mechanisms, so we need an adapter in between.
这个适配器叫"加压对接适配舱" 简称PMA
This is called the pressurized mating adapter, or PMA for short.
大头侧使用CBM 可以连接空间站的美国段
The larger side uses CBM, which can be attached to the US side of the station.
Androgynous Peripheral Attach System(APAS)
异体同构周边式对接系统
小头侧使用APAS
The smaller side uses APAS.
它可以连接俄罗斯侧的舱段和航天飞机
This is compatible with the Russian side of the station and with the space shuttle.
截至目前 国际空间站上共有三个PMA
On this station today, there are three of these adapters.
PMA-1用于美国段与俄罗斯段之间的永久连接
PMA-1 is permanently in place connecting the two sides of the station.
PMA-2与PMA-3用于对接航天飞机
PMA-2 and PMA-3 were used as docking ports for the space shuttle.
它的小头侧 使用APAS 用来连接航天飞机
The smaller side, which is the side that uses APAS, was used for the space shuttle.
航天飞机就是使用它与空间站对接的
This is how it would dock to the space station.
国际对接适配器 IDA
这两个PMA末端现在都加装了另外一种适配器
Both of these PMAs now have yet another type of adapter placed at the end.
让现代航天器有能力与国际空间站对接
This allows for more modern spacecraft to dock to the space station.
av437185351 16分开始
这部分的详细内容可以观看之前介绍载人龙飞船的视频
If you'd like to see this in action, you can watch my SpaceX Crew Dragon video.
视频链接在下方
I'll leave a link in the description below.
我们快速介绍一下航天飞机
Now, let's take a quick look at this space shuttle.
乘组多数时间在机组舱内
The crew spends most of their time up here in the crew compartment.
后部是载荷舱
Back here is the payload bay.
空间站的舱段就是放在这里发射进入太空的
This is where the space station modules were carried up into space.
前部是轨道对接系统
Up front here is the orbital docking system.
航天飞机通过这里与国际空间站对接
This is the place they could dock to the International Space Station.
宇航员还可以通过侧面这个舱门进行出舱行走
The astronauts can also do spacewalks from out of this hatch.
侧面这里是加拿大臂
On the side here is the Canadarm.
可以在太空中抓取并移动设备
It's a robotic arm that is capable of moving things around in space.
机械臂可以由画面中航天飞机的工作台操控
The arm can be controlled from inside of the space shuttle at this workstation.
航天飞机从佛罗里达州的肯尼迪航天中心发射升空
The space shuttle launches took place from Kennedy Space Center in Florida.
进入太空后 载荷舱舱门开启
Once in space, the payload bay doors were opened.
并在整个太空飞行中一直保持开启
They remained open for the entire time they were in space.
之后航天飞机会花几天时间追上国际空间站
Then it took a few days for the space shuttle to catch up with the ISS.
航天飞机如今已退役 但它在国际空间站的建设中发挥了关键作用
The space shuttle is retired now, but it played a crucial role in building the space station.
我们来了解航天飞机其中几次任务
Let's take a look at a few of these space shuttle missions.
第一个任务我们会讲得详细一点
This first mission we'll go over in a bit more detail.
我会给出时间线 与每个作业时长
I wanna give an idea for the timeline and how long things took.
而之后三个任务 我会快速略过 让大家有个概念即可
And then for the next three missions,
we'll go over just a little bit quicker once we get the right idea.
我要介绍的第一个任务是1998年12月的STS-88
The first mission we'll talk about is STS-88 in December of 1998.
"STS"全称"太空运输系统"
And the STS stands for Space Transportation System.
所有航天飞机任务都由这三个字母开头
All shuttle missions started with these three letters.
该任务是航天飞机执行的首个国际空间站任务
This was the first shuttle mission to the International Space Station.
曙光号功能货仓在1998年11月由俄罗斯质子号火箭发射
此时 空间站只有一个舱段
At this time, the station had only one piece.
俄罗斯的曙光号功能货仓独自绕地球飞行
It was the Russian module Zarya orbiting the earth all by itself.
它在整个空间站中位置如画面所示
On the completed station, this is where Zarya is.
而首次航天飞机任务将团结号节点舱送入太空
And this first shuttle mission brought up the Unity Module.
它的作用就像空间站的"集线器"一样
This is kind of like the center hub of the station
上面有六个停泊口可供其他舱段连接
with six berthing ports where other modules can be attached.
与团结号一同上天的还有PMA-1和PMA-2
Unity was launched with PMA-1 and PMA-2 already attached to it.
此次任务共耗时近12天
This mission took almost 12 days to complete.
前几天用来进行前期准备 和与曙光号交会
The first few days were used to make preparations and to catch up to Zarya.
任务第三天 加拿大臂开始工作
On day three of the mission, the Canadarm was put to work.
该从载荷舱中抓起团结号了
It was time to lift Unity out of the payload bay.
它将PMA-2与航天飞机对接口对接
PMA-2 was then attached to the orbital docking system on the shuttle.
加拿大臂可以在太空的失重环境下移动大质量物体
The Canadarm can move large masses in space due to being weightless while an orbit.
为了不破坏机械臂关节 移动需要非常慢
It had to move very slowly to not strain the robotic joints.
整个过程需要极其小心 花费数小时
It took hours to complete and very careful movement .
航天飞机的推进器还会启动 来辅助与舱段对接
The shuttle's thrusters were fired to bring the modules together.
在任务第四天 航天飞机缓慢靠近曙光号
On the fourth day of the mission, the space shuttle slowly approached Zarya.
然后加拿大臂捕获曙光号
The Canadarm grabbed onto it,
将它挪到PMA-1上方
and then moved it into position above PMA-1.
同样 航天飞机推进器启动 将两者对接起来
Again, the shuttle's thrusters were fired to bring the modules together.
在乘组可以进入空间站前 还需要几天的准备
It took a few more days of preparation before they could go inside the station.
他们穿上舱外宇航服 进行了两次太空行走
There were two EVAs where they get into their spacesuit and go outside the station.
在舱段外部连接了线缆 安装了天线
They connected cables and installed antennas on the outside of the station.
加拿大臂还用来辅助宇航员在舱外作业时的移动
The Canadarm was used to help move the astronauts around.
任务第八天 他们首次打开了舱门 进入了国际空间站
On the eighth day of the mission, they opened the hatch and entered the station for the first time.
他们只在空间站内驻留了大约一天
They only stayed inside for about a day,
刚好能做些检查 并为下次任务做准备
just enough to check things out and prepare it for the next mission.
任务第十天 乘组再次执行一次太空行走 完成最后的安装工作
On the 10th day of the mission, there was one more EVA to finish the installation.
任务第十一天 航天飞机与国际空间站分离
Then on the 11th day of the mission, the shuttle undocked from the ISS.
此时 空间站上还没有长期驻留的宇航员
At this point, there was no permanent crew yet.
空间站还太小
The station was too small.
团结号和曙光号共同无人飞行了几个月的时间
Unity and Zarya orbited all by themselves for the next few months,
当然 一切都是在地面任务控制中心的掌握中
of course, all while being monitored by mission control back on Earth.
我们把时间快进几年
Now we'll fast forward just a few years in time.
现在国际空间站又新增了几个舱段
The station had a few more modules,
上面还有三名宇航员生活
and there were three crew members living on board the station.
我们要讲的下个任务是2001年2月的STS-98
The next mission we'll talk about is STS-98 in February of 2001.
完工的空间站是这样的
So here's our completed station.
而STS-98之前它长这样
Here's what it looked like right before STS-98.
此次任务为空间站带来了命运号实验舱
This mission brought up the Destiny Module.
STS-98任务持续13天
STS-98 lasted for 13 days,
其中只有6天是与空间站对接的状态
but they were attached to the station for only six of those days.
航天飞机与国际空间站底部 径向向内的PMA-3对接口对接
They docked a PMA-3 on the nadir, or bottom side of the station.
加拿大臂捕获PMA-2
The Canadarm was used to grab onto PMA-2
并把它暂时置于Z1桁架上
and relocate it to the side of the Z1 Truss.
随后加拿大臂拿出载荷舱中的命运号
Then the arm was used to lift the Destiny Module out of the payload bay,
慢慢翻转180度
slowly flip it 180 degrees,
并将它与团结号的前向停泊口对接
and then attach it to the forward berthing port on Unity.
这一操作花费了数小时 需要极其小心地移动 防止损坏设备
This took hours to complete and very careful movement to make sure nothing was damaged.
次日 乘组首次打开舱门 进入命运号
The next day, they opened the hatches and went inside Destiny for the first time.
命运号美国实验舱主要用于空间站内的科学研究
US laboratory is mainly used for scientific research on board the station.
随后PMA-2移动到命运号的前向停泊口
PMA-2 was then relocated to the forward side of Destiny.
整个任务期间 一共执行了三次太空行走
The mission had three separate EVAs
在空间站外进行了连接与安装设备的作业
to connect and install items on the outside of the station.
下一任务目标是为空间站加装一个自己的机械臂——加拿大臂2
The purpose of this next mission
was to give the station its own robotic arm called the Canadarm2.
第一个加拿大臂是航天飞机上的
The first Canadarm was on the space shuttle.
用处很大 但它是固定在航天飞机上的
Very useful, but it was permanently attached to the shuttle.
所以每次航天飞机任务结束都会跟着返回地面
This means it goes home at the end of a shuttle mission.
而加拿大臂2现在可以在空间站上抓取重型载荷了
The Canadarm2 can lift heavier loads and would now stay onboard the station,
在两次航天飞机任务之间也能正常使用
so it can be used in between shuttle missions.
画面所示 是如今可能在空间站上发现加拿大臂2的位置
Here's an example of where you might find the Canadarm2 on the station today.
机械臂的两端都能与空间站相连
The arm can attach to the station at either end.
它们称为"锁合末端效应器"
These are called Latching End Effectors.
PDGF: 电力和数据传输型锚钩固定装置
它可以与空间站上所有PDGF连接
It attaches to anywhere on the station that has a power data grapple fixture.
顾名思义 它可以传输电力与数据
As you might guess, it provides power and data connection,
因此它可以从空间站内部进行控制
so it can be controlled from inside the station
需要时 还可由地面任务控制中心控制
and from mission control back on Earth if needed.
国际空间站外部有很多PDGF
These power data grapple fixtures are in many places on the outside of the station.
加拿大臂2在STS-100任务中进入太空
The mission that brought up the Canadarm2 was called STS-100.
任务时长12天
It was a 12-day mission.
航天飞机与空间站前向的PMA-2对接口对接
The shuttle docked to the front of the station at PMA-2.
这个舱段类似于后来的货运飞船
可以上行补给 可以下行货物
一共有三艘 每次跟随航天飞机入轨并返回
在轨时会暂时与空间站对接
航天飞机携带了拉斐尔多用途后勤模组
This carried Raffaello, a multi-purpose logistics module,
它会暂时与空间站连接
which would be temporarily attached to the station.
第二件载荷就是加拿大臂2
The second piece of cargo was the Canadarm2.
它在载荷舱内是收纳在一个特制平台上的
It was brought to the station on onboard a special pallet.
航天飞机加拿大臂抓起平台 从载荷舱内拿出
The shuttle's Canadarm grabbed onto the pallet, lifted it out of the payload bay,
把平台放置在命运号上方
and then attached the pallet to the top of the Destiny Module.
宇航员慢慢把它展开并组装好
It was slowly unfolded and put together by the astronauts.
宇航员也得到了航天飞机加拿大臂的一点点帮助
They also had a little help from the shuttle's Canadarm.
随后 加拿大臂2首次自行移动
Then the Canadarm2 was moved on its own for the first time.
它最先与命运号侧面相连
It was initially connected to the side of the Destiny Module.
任务末尾 加拿大臂2把刚刚的平台抓起 "递给"了航天飞机加拿大臂
At the end of the mission,
the Canadarm2 was used to lift the pallet and hand over to the shuttle's Canadarm.
这是机械臂首次在太空中的"握手"
This was the first robotic handshake in space,
也有称"加拿大之握"
sometimes referred to as the Canadian handshake
因为两支机械臂都是由加拿大制造的
because both of these arms were built by Canada.
用完空置的平台随后又放回载荷舱
The empty pallet was then put back into the payload bay.
几天后 航天飞机与空间站分离
A few days later, the shuttled undocked from the station.
加拿大臂2执行了之后空间站的主要建造工作
The Canadarm2 was essential for constructing the rest of the space station.
本期视频最后想介绍的任务是STS-104
The last mission that I wanna show in this video is STS-104.
画面中是完工的空间站
So here's the completed station,
而STS-104任务前长这样
and here's what it looked like right before STS-104.
此次任务为空间站带来了寻求号气密舱
This mission brought up the Quest Airlock.
任务时长近13天
The mission lasted for almost 13 days.
航天飞机再次与空间站前向PMA-2对接口对接
Once again, docking to the front of the station at PMA-2.
这是他们首次使用加拿大臂2来建造空间站
This was the first time they used the Canadarm2 to help construct the station.
它把寻求号气密舱缓慢移动到团结号的右舷处
The Quest Airlock was slowly moved into position on the starboard side of the Unity Module.
两位宇航员此时已准备好辅助新舱段的安装工作
Two of the astronauts were in position ready to help install the new module.
寻求号安装好后 该安装高压储气罐了
Once Quest was installed, it was time for the high pressure gas tanks.
高压储气罐同样使用加拿大臂2移动
Once again, the Canadarm2 was used to move the tanks around.
宇航员辅助储气罐移动到正确位置
The astronauts helped guide the tanks into position.
在此之前 宇航员只能使用航天飞机载荷舱的出口出舱
Up until this point, they could only perform spacewalks from the shuttle's payload bay,
但有了寻求号气密舱后 他们就多了一个选择
but the Quest Airlock gave them another option.
矮粗的部分是"装备段"
This part is called the equipment lock,
细长部分是"乘员段"
and this part is called the crew lock.
宇航员在当中穿好舱外宇航服后
Once the astronauts are inside of their spacesuits,
关好内部舱门 乘员段减压
the hatch is closed, and the crew lock is depressurized.
即抽掉其中的所有空气
This means that all the air is pumped out.
然后打开气密舱舱门
Now the airlock hatch is opened,
再打开外部的隔热罩
and then the thermal cover on the outside.
舱门开口为径向向内
The opening points straight down.
所以宇航员开门后第一眼是空间站下方的地球
So the first thing they see is the Earth right beneath them.
本期视频总结了航天飞机的四次任务
This video summarized four separate shuttle missions,
让大家能更好了解国际空间站的建设经历
just to give you a better idea of what it took to construct the International Space Station.
这些还只是早期阶段
This was just the early stages,
国际空间站的建设还有很多工作要完成
and there's a lot more to the construction.
我或许会在未来视频中继续为大家介绍
Maybe we'll cover that in a future video.
我是Jared 感谢观看
My name's Jared. Thanks for watching.